{
    "questions":[
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following rivers is not the tributary of Ganga ?",
            "optionA": "  Indrawati ",
            "optionB": "  Son ",
            "optionC": "  Gomati ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Indrawati rivers is not the tributary of Ganga. It is a tributary of the Godavari River, in central India.",
            "keyString": "81279s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Yamuna and the Sone are the tributaries of the river",
            "optionA": "  Jhelam ",
            "optionB": "  Beas ",
            "optionC": "  Ravi ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The Yamuna and the Sone are the tributaries of the river Ganga. The Yamuna River is one of the most beautiful rivers of India. It is the biggest tributary of the Ganges (also known as Ganga) in Northern India. Son River, Son also spelled Sone, principal southern tributary of the Ganges (Ganga) River, rising in Madhya Pradesh state, central India. ",
            "keyString": "81470s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct sequence of these rivers when arranged in the North - South direction is :1. Kishenganga2. Ganga3. Wainganga4. Penganga",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 1, 3, 4 ",
            "optionC": "  2, 1, 4, 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 4, 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The correct sequence of these rivers when arranged in the North - South direction is Kishenganga, Ganga, Wainganga and Penganga. ",
            "keyString": "81634s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers existed before the uplift of the Himalaya ? (A) Brahamaputra(B) Sutlej(C) Indus(D) Bhagirathi",
            "optionA": "  A and C ",
            "optionB": "  B and C ",
            "optionC": "  A, B and C ",
            "optionD": "  A, B, C and D ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Brahamaputra, Sutlej and Indus rivers existed before the uplift of the Himalaya. ",
            "keyString": "81723s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following rivers from South to North: 1. Cauvery2. Krishna3. Godavari4. Mahanadi",
            "optionA": "  1, 3, 2, 4 ",
            "optionB": "  3, 4, 1, 2 ",
            "optionC": "  2, 4, 3, 1 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The following rivers from South to North are Cauvery, Krishna, Godavari and Mahanadi. ",
            "keyString": "81808s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is India's largest multipurpose river valley project?",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra Nangal ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar Valley ",
            "optionC": "  Nagarjunasagar ",
            "optionD": "  Thungabhadra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Bhakra Nangal is India's largest multipurpose river valley project. It is the largest and the most important multipurpose project named after the two dams built at Bhakra and Nangal on the Satluj River. ",
            "keyString": "81886s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most rivers flowing west from the Western Ghats do not form deltas because of",
            "optionA": "  Lack of eroded material ",
            "optionB": "  The high gradient ",
            "optionC": "  Lack of vegetation free area ",
            "optionD": "  Low velocity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Most rivers flowing west from the Western Ghats do not form deltas because of the high gradient and they don't have to travel much distance to drain into the sea. As a result, they don't carry much sediments because they don't have the time to. This prevents them from forming deltas at their mouths and mostly only estuaries are formed. ",
            "keyString": "81965s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following groups of rivers have their source of origin in Tibet?",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra, Indus & Sutlej ",
            "optionB": "  Ganga, Sutlej & Yamuna ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra, Ganga & Sutlej ",
            "optionD": "  Chenab, Ravi & Sutlej ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Brahmaputra, Indus & Sutlej have their source of origin in Tibet. ",
            "keyString": "82051s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second largest east-flowing Peninsular river is",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The second largest east-flowing Peninsular river is Krishna, it rises north of mahabaleshwara. ",
            "keyString": "82127s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In northeast India,river flows out of the country is",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionB": "  Gandak ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Brahmaputra flows out of Indian territory and it enters Bangladesh where it is locally known as Jamuna and then it drains in bey Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "82205s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Majuli, the World's largest river Island is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Tripura ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Majuli is a riverine island located on Brahmaputra river in Assam.It is the first Island district of India. ",
            "keyString": "82279s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river does not relate with Punjab?",
            "optionA": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionB": "  Ravi ",
            "optionC": "  Beas ",
            "optionD": "  Tapti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Tapti river originates from Betul plateau in Madhya Pradesh and its river basin lies in M.P., Maharashtra and Gujarat. So it not related to Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "82353s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sivasamudram is an island formed by the river",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "   Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sivasamudram Island is a small city in the Mandya district of Karnataka. It lies on the bank of river Cauvery. ",
            "keyString": "82426s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river flow from south to north direction?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "  Son ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Son river originates from Arnarkantak Plateau and flow towards northward plains where it meets Ganga near Patna. It is a right bank tributary of river Ganga.",
            "keyString": "82500s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Nagarjunasagar Project is an important multipurpose project on the river ________ in the ________ district of Andhra Pradesh.",
            "optionA": "  Godavari, West Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Mahanadi, Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna, Nalgonda ",
            "optionD": "  Tungabhadra, East Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Nagarjunasagar Project is an important multipurpose project on the river Krishna in the Nalgonda district of Andhra Pradesh. This Project is a venture of Andhra Pradesh for utilizing water of the Krishna River. The Nagarjunasagar Dam was inaugurated on Aug 4, 1967. It is situated near Nandikonda village in Miryalguda Taluk of Nalgonda district. ",
            "keyString": "82575s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The joint river valley venture of India and Nepal is",
            "optionA": "  Gomati ",
            "optionB": "  Chambal ",
            "optionC": "  Damodar ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Kosi also known as \"Sorrow of Bihar\" rises in Nepal and is a confluence of 7 rivers termed as Saptkoshi. It is a joint venture of India and Nepal. ",
            "keyString": "82655s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river is famous for changing its path?",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Kosi ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Damodar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Kosi river also known as \"Sorrow of Bihar\" carries huge amount of water and sediments and when it enters plains itchanges its coarse regularly and huge amount of sediments deposit in very less time leading to overflow of water which causes devastating floods in Bihar specially in Monsoons. ",
            "keyString": "82728s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following rivers thrice forks into two streams and reunites a few miles farther on, thus forming the islands of Srirangapatanam, Sivasamudram and Srirangam?",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionB": "  Tungabhadra ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Cauvery rivers thrice forks into two streams and reunites a few miles farther on, thus forming the islands of Srirangapatanam, Sivasamudram and Srirangam. ",
            "keyString": "82789s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following Indian rivers does not have a delta at its egress?",
            "optionA": "  Tapi ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Tapi river does not have a delta at its egress. The Tapi River is also known as the Tapti River. Tapti is the prehistoric Sanskrit name of the river. Tapi is a major River in central India . With a stretch of about 724 km, it is also one of the most crucial rivers in peninsular India.",
            "keyString": "82814s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following rivers:1. Betwa2. Kosi3. GandakWhich of the above joint(s) Yamuna river?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The Betwa River is mentioned in the epic Mahabharata along with the Charmanwati River, which is now called the Chambal River. Both are tributaries of Yamuna. Chambal and Betwa join Yamuna at the Etawah district and Hamirpur town in Uttarpradesh.",
            "keyString": "82835s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Damodar-Tribeni Canal which serves as an irrigation cum-navigation canal is ________ long.",
            "optionA": "  137km ",
            "optionB": "  147km ",
            "optionC": "  157km ",
            "optionD": "  167km ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The Damodar-Tribeni Canal which serves as an irrigation cum-navigation canal is 137km long. ",
            "keyString": "82855s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river Damodar ends in",
            "optionA": "  River Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  River Hugli ",
            "optionC": "  The Bay of Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Salt Lake ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The river Damodar ends in River Hugli. It joins Hooghly river in Hooghly district, in West Bengal and the river drains in Bay of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "82873s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest multipurpose dam built on the river Ravi is",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra Nangal ",
            "optionB": "  Kahalgaon ",
            "optionC": "  Ranjit Sagar dam ",
            "optionD": "  Rihand dam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Also Known as Thein Dam. Ranjit Sagar Dam is hydroelectric project on river Ravi. It is shared by Punjab and Jammu and Kashmir. Its height is 160m and it is used for both irrigation as well as power generation. ",
            "keyString": "82891s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shyok is a tributary of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Chenab ",
            "optionD": "  Sutlej ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Shyok is a tributary of Indus. The Shyok River, a tributary of the Indus River, originates from the Rimo Glacier which is believed to be one of the tongues of Siachen Glacier. ",
            "keyString": "82911s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an inland drainage area?",
            "optionA": "  Sambhar area ",
            "optionB": "  Chilka region ",
            "optionC": "  Mansarovar lake ",
            "optionD": "  Rann of Kutch ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Rann of Kutch is an inland drainage area. Inland drainage is that drainage in which rivers do not reach an ocean or sea but empty their waters in a lake or an inland sea.",
            "keyString": "82930s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rajasthan Canal (now called the Indira Gandhi Canal) draws its water from the",
            "optionA": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionB": "  Chambal ",
            "optionC": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionD": "  Sutlej and Beas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The Rajasthan Canal (now called the Indira Gandhi Canal) draws its water from the Sutlej and Beas. The canal was earlier known as Rajasthan Canal and its name was changed in 1984. Indira Gandhi Canal uses water released from Pong dam. The 649-km long main canal carrying waters from Satluj and Beas rivers of Punjab serves a large part of north west Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "82948s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tochi, Gilgit and Hunza are tributaries of",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Tochi, Gilgit and Hunza are tributaries of Indus. ",
            "keyString": "82968s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following areas, the widest continental shelf of India is found ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Around the Gulf of Cambay ",
            "optionB": "  Around the Konkan coast ",
            "optionC": "  Off the Krishna and Godavari deltas ",
            "optionD": "  Around the Palk strait ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Among the following areas, the widest continental shelf of India is found off the Krishna and Godavari deltas. ",
            "keyString": "82985s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ports are on the west coast?1. Marmugao2. Cochin3. New Mangalore4. Paradeep",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Marmugao, Cochin and New Mangalore ports are on the west coast. ",
            "keyString": "83004s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The worst affected state of India by the menace of sea erosion is",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Odisha ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The worst affected state of India by the menace of sea erosion is Kerala. Kerala is the state which is worst affected by coastal erosion in India. Efforts are being made to counter the menace of coastal erosion and to. ",
            "keyString": "83021s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following south Indian rivers has the largest basin?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Godavari rivers has the largest basin. The river Godavari is the largest of the peninsular rivers of India. Maharashtra is home for its early flows and Godavari for Maharashtra is no less than Ganga. Referred to as Dakshin Ganga the river holds immense spiritual and cultural significance.",
            "keyString": "83040s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers lies in a rift valley?",
            "optionA": "  Luni ",
            "optionB": "  Chambal ",
            "optionC": "  Son ",
            "optionD": "  Tapi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Tapi river lies in a rift valley. A rift valley is created on a divergent plate boundary by action of a fault or rift. ",
            "keyString": "83063s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct sequence of the eastward flowing rivers of the peninsular India from north to south is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Subarnarekha, Mahanadi, Godavari, Krishna, Pennar, Cauvery and Vagai ",
            "optionB": "  Subarnarekha, Mahanadi, Krishna, Godavari, Cauvery, Vagai and Pennar ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi, Subarnarekha, Godavari, Krishna, Cauvery, Pennar and Vagai ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi, Subarnarekha, Krishna, Godavari, Cauvery, Vagai and Pennar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The correct sequence of the eastward flowing rivers of the peninsular India from north to south is Subarnarekha, Mahanadi, Godavari, Krishna, Pennar, Cauvery and Vagai. ",
            "keyString": "83082s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The youngest rivers in India originate from",
            "optionA": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionB": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionC": "  Himalayas ",
            "optionD": "  Deccan Plateau ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The youngest rivers in India originate from Himalayas. The Himalayas are among the youngest mountain ranges on the planet. Major Rivers originating from the Himalayas such as River Ganga, Brahmaputra and Indus.",
            "keyString": "83104s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Indian state is known as 'Land of Five Rivers' ?",
            "optionA": "  U.P. ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Punjab is known as 'Land of Five Rivers'. The word \"Punjab\" is a combination of the Persian words panj (five), and \u0101b (water), giving the literal meaning of the \"Land of Five Rivers\". The five rivers after which Punjab is named are the Beas, Jhelum, Chenab, Ravi and Sutlej.",
            "keyString": "83122s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following rivers has the largest catchment area?",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Krishna rivers has the largest catchment area. It is the fourth largest river in India after the Ganga, Godavari and the Narmada.",
            "keyString": "83150s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the longest river in India?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Ganga is the longest river in India. Ganges - 2,525 km. The Ganges River is one of the country's longest rivers, as well as its most famous. Also called the Ganga, the Ganges River rises in the western Himalayas of India, and flows throughout the north of the country before it travels to the Bay of Bengal through Bangladesh. ",
            "keyString": "83168s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the decreasing order of the length of the rivers, the correct sequence is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra - Ganga - Godavari - Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Ganga - Godavari - Brahmaputra - Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra - Narmada - Godavari - Ganga ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga - Brahmaputra - Godavari \u2013 Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "In the decreasing order of the length of the rivers, the correct sequence is Brahmaputra - Ganga - Godavari - Narmada. ",
            "keyString": "83188s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? River City",
            "optionA": "  Gomti Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Saryu Ayodhya ",
            "optionC": "  Alaknanda Badrinath ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada Satna ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Narmada first follows a tortuous course through the hills near Mandla and then turns northwest to pass the city of Jabalpur. ",
            "keyString": "83210s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The city located on the river Yamuna is",
            "optionA": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionB": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionC": "  Patna ",
            "optionD": "  Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The city located on the river Yamuna is Agra. Agra is a city in the state of Uttar Pradesh in India which situates in the banks of River Yamuna. The Yamuna river sometimes called Jamuna, Kalindi river are lifeline of cities like Delhi and Agra. It was the capital city during the Mughal period. ",
            "keyString": "83229s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ river is sometimes referred to as \"Dakshin Ganga\".",
            "optionA": "  Panner ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Godavari is sometimes referred to as \"Dakshin Ganga\". ",
            "keyString": "83248s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which river flows between Satpura and Vindhyas?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Gandak ",
            "optionC": "  Tapti ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Narmada river after originating from Amarkantak Plateau flows through a rift valley bounded by Vindhyas in North and Satpura in south. ",
            "keyString": "83264s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river does not form a delta?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Tapti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Tapti is a west flowing river. It flows through a rift valley of Igneous rocks so it is not able to collect much sediments and hence it forms an Estuary instead of a Delta. ",
            "keyString": "83281s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Hirakud Project harnesses the water of the ________ river.",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Tapi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Hirakud Project harnesses the water of the Mahanadi river. The multi-purpose Hirakud Dam constructed across the river Mahanadi. The aim of this project was to control flood, supply water for irrigation purpose and hydropower power generation. The construction of dam was started as in 1940's. The first notification for the land acquisition was issued on 13 September 1946. ",
            "keyString": "83299s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following rivers:1. Ganga2. Brahmaputra3. Godavari4. KrishnaWhich of these rivers build a common delta?",
            "optionA": "  1 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Ganga and Brahmaputra rivers build a common delta. Ganges Delta also known as Sunderbans Delta or Ganges Brahmaputra Delta in the Bengal region of the Indian subcontinent. This Green Delta is largest delta in the world and empties into the Bay of Bengal with combined Brahmaputra and the Ganges river. ",
            "keyString": "83322s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct sequence of the following ports from north to south? 1. Karaikal2. Machilipatnam3. Paradeep4. Visakhapatnam",
            "optionA": "  1-2-4-3 ",
            "optionB": "  1-4-2-3 ",
            "optionC": "  3-2-4-1 ",
            "optionD": "  3-4-2-1 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The correct sequence of the following ports from north to south are Paradeep, Visakhapatnam, Machilipatnam and Karaikal. ",
            "keyString": "83348s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the first company-managed major port in India?",
            "optionA": "  Cochin ",
            "optionB": "  Ennore ",
            "optionC": "  Tuticorin ",
            "optionD": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Ennore is the first company-managed major port in India. This port is now named as Kamarajar Port Limited. It is first corporate port of India and is registered as a public company with 68% stake held by government. ",
            "keyString": "104098s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The highest waterfall in India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Sivasundaram ",
            "optionB": "  Jog ",
            "optionC": "  Courtallam ",
            "optionD": "  Hogenakal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The highest waterfall in India is Jog. Jog water falls created by the Sharavathi river in sharavathi valley of Shimoga district in Karnataka. Its breathtaking spectacle when Sharavathi river falling from a height of 829 ft. It is the most impressive and one of the highest plunge waterfalls in India. ",
            "keyString": "104165s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the deepest landlocked protected port?",
            "optionA": "  Kandla ",
            "optionB": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "optionC": "  Haldia ",
            "optionD": "  Tuticorin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Vishakhapatnam is the deepest landlocked protected port. Visakhapatnam Port is one of 13 major ports in India and the only major port of Andhra Pradesh. It is India's second largest port by volume of cargo handled. ",
            "keyString": "104193s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By what name is the Ganga known in Bangladesh?",
            "optionA": "  Padma ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagirathi ",
            "optionC": "  Rupnarayan ",
            "optionD": "  Nubra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Ganga is known as Padma in Bangladesh. After entering Bangladesh, the main branch of Ganga is known as the Padma. The Padma is joined by the Jamuna River, the largest distributary of the Brahmaputra. ",
            "keyString": "104216s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buckingham Canal runs through",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu and Karnataka ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu and Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The Buckingham Canal runs through Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu. The Buckingham Canal is a 796 kilometres long fresh water navigation canal, running parallel to the Coromandel Coast of South India from Kakinada in East Godavari district in Andhra Pradesh to Villupuram District in Tamil Nadu.",
            "keyString": "104237s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest irrigation canal in India",
            "optionA": "  Yamuna canal ",
            "optionB": "  Indira Gandhi canal ",
            "optionC": "  Sirhand canal ",
            "optionD": "  Upper Bari Doab canal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Indira Gandhi canal is the largest canal project in India with an approximate length of about 643 km. As it does not serve water to Punjab and mainly supplies water to Rajasthan it is also known as Rajasthan feeder. ",
            "keyString": "104257s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Tulbul Project - Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Srisailam Project - Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Papanasam Project - Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Ukai Project - Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Project -State Ukai-Gujarat Tulbul-J & KSrisailam - Andhra Pradesh Papanasam- Tamil Nadu ",
            "keyString": "104275s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Buckincham Canal is an inland water way in",
            "optionA": "  United Kingdom ",
            "optionB": "  Australia ",
            "optionC": "  India ",
            "optionD": "  New Zealand ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Buckincham Canal is an inland water way in India. The Buckingham Canal is a 796 kilometres (494.6 mi) long fresh water navigation canal, that parallels the Coromandel Coast of South India from Kakinada in the East Godavari district of Andhra Pradesh to Villupuram District in Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "104294s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs of sea ports and states is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Kandla : Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Paradip : Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Quilon : Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Kakinada : Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Kakinada Port is located at Kakinada off the east coast of India. It is 170 km (106 mi) south of Visakhapatnam Port. ",
            "keyString": "104469s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following groups of rivers fall in the Bay of Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga, Brahmaputra, Hooghly ",
            "optionB": "  Ganga, Yamuna, Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga, Yamuna, Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga, Yamuna, Gandak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Ganga, Brahmaputra, Hooghly groups of rivers fall in the Bay of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "104498s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following east flowing rivers of India has rift valley due to down warping",
            "optionA": "  Damodar ",
            "optionB": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionC": "  Sone ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Damodar is a east flowing river with rift valley due to down warping. Down warp denotes a segment of the earth\u2019s crust that is broadly bent downward. ",
            "keyString": "104516s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements about the Himalayan rivers is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  They have very large basins ",
            "optionB": "  Many of them pass through giant gorges ",
            "optionC": "  They perform very little erosion activity ",
            "optionD": "  Over the plain they display a strong meandering tendency and often shift their beds ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "They perform very little erosion activity is not correct about Himalayan River. They perform intensive erosional activity in their upper courses to carry huge loads of silt and sand while it reaches the downstream the Melting glaciers increases the flow of water due to which hugeamount of sediments and deprives plains of the essential nutrients. ",
            "keyString": "104542s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which river is known as \"Open Sewer\" in India?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada ",
            "optionD": "  Godayari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Industrial waste and sewage disposal have lead to heavy pollution in River Yamuna that is why it is often termed as open sewage or \"khula naala\" ",
            "keyString": "104565s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs are correctly matched? Waterfall : River1. Kapildhara Falls : Godavari2. Jog Falls : Sharavati3. Sivasamudram Falls : Cauvery",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The following pairs that are correctly matched are Jog Falls : Sharavati and Sivasamudram Falls : Cauvery. ",
            "keyString": "104583s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Study of Lakes is called",
            "optionA": "  Limnology ",
            "optionB": "  Potomology ",
            "optionC": "  Topology ",
            "optionD": "  Hydrology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The study of inland fresh waters whether of standing bodies like lakes or dynamic bodies like rivers along with their drainage basins is termed as Limnology. ",
            "keyString": "104600s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is called the \"Lake District of India\"?",
            "optionA": "  Nainital ",
            "optionB": "  Shimla ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Matheran ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Nainital Lake is called the \"Lake district of India\". Nainital Lake is one of the four lakes of Kumaon Hills, the other three lakes are Sattal Lake, the Bhimtal Lake and Naukuchiyatal Lake, these lakes are of \"tactonic origin\". The district of Nainital is in the Kumaon region of India's Uttarakhand state. Nainital is named after the Hindu diety \"Naina Devi\", whose temple is situated on the northern shore of \"Nainital Lake\". ",
            "keyString": "104629s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ________ Lake of India has very high salinity.",
            "optionA": "  Sambhar (Rajasthan) ",
            "optionB": "  Wular (Jammu & Kashmir) ",
            "optionC": "  Chilka (Odisha) ",
            "optionD": "  Pulicut (Tamil Nadu) ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The Sambhar (Rajasthan) Lake of India has very high salinity. The Sambhar Lake of Rajasthan is about 233 sq km in extent, it is known to have a large reserves of salt in its bottom layers. ",
            "keyString": "104797s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The biggest lake in India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Dal Lake ",
            "optionB": "  Chilka Lake ",
            "optionC": "  Wular Lake ",
            "optionD": "  Sambhar Lake ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The biggest lake in India is Chilka Lake. Chilka Lake is a brackish water lagoon. It is the largest lake of India measuring approximately 1165 sq. kilometers. Chilka lake is thus the largest salt water lake of India. It is also the largest wintering ground for migratory birds on the Indian subcontinent. ",
            "keyString": "104824s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following:1. Chilika Lake2. Pulicat Lake3. Vembanad LakeWhich of the above is/are lagoon(s)?",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Chilika Lake, Pulicat Lake and Vembanad Lake all three are lagoons. ",
            "keyString": "104843s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river which rises in the Kamarpet hill in Chhotanagpur Plateau of Bihar and called \"The River of Sorrow\" is",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The river which rises in the Kamarpet hill in Chhotanagpur Plateau of Bihar and called \"The River of Sorrow\" is Damodar. Damodar River was earlier known as the \"River of Sorrows\" as it used to flood many areas of Bardhaman, Hooghly,Howrah and Medinipur districts. Even now the floods sometimes affect the lower Damodar Valley, but the havoc it wreaked in earlier years is now a matter of history. ",
            "keyString": "104860s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a trans-Himalayan river?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionC": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionD": "  Ravi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Sutlej is a trans-Himalayan river. The Trans-Himalayan Rivers\u00a0originate beyond the Great\u00a0Himalayas. These are the Indus, the Sutlej and the Brahmaputra\u00a0rivers.\u00a0Himalayan rivers\u00a0are those which originate in theHimalayas\u00a0and flow through the Northern Plains, e.g., the Ganga, the Yamuna and their tributaries. ",
            "keyString": "104880s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Alamatti is on the river",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Alamatti is on the river Krishna. The Alamatti reservoir built across River Krishna has reached the maximum level due to heavy rainfall in Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "104904s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an inland riverine port?",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "   Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  Tuticorin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Kolkata is an inland riverine port. It is situated along the Hoogly river. ",
            "keyString": "105071s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main river flowing in the state of Jammu and Kashmir is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Jhelum ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Chenab ",
            "optionD": "  Nubra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The main river flowing in the state of Jammu and Kashmir is Jhelum. The Jhelum River is the only major Himalayan river which flows through the Kashmir valley. The Indus, Tawi, Ravi and Chenab are the other major rivers flowing through the state. ",
            "keyString": "105096s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following rivers in descending order of their length:1. Ravi2. Cauvery3. Sutlej4. Yamuna",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 4, 3 ",
            "optionB": "  3, 4, 1, 2 ",
            "optionC": "  4, 3, 2, 1 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The following rivers in descending order of their length are Yamuna, Sutlej, Cauvery and Ravi. ",
            "keyString": "105115s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which are the west-flowing rivers of southern Indian which flow into Arabian Sea?",
            "optionA": "  Chambal and Betwa ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar and Mahanadi ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada and Tapti ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna and Cauveri ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Narmada and Tapti are the west-flowing rivers of southern Indian which flow into Arabian Sea. The two major west flowing rivers are the Narmada and the Tapi. This exceptional behavior is because these rivers didn\u2019t form valleys and instead they flow through faults (linear rift, rift valley, trough) created due to the bending of the northern peninsula during the formation process of Himalayas. ",
            "keyString": "105132s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Marmagao port is linked to the interior by means of cheap transport on rivers",
            "optionA": "  Zuari and Mandovi ",
            "optionB": "  Bhima and Kalinadi ",
            "optionC": "  Varada and Malaprabha ",
            "optionD": "  Gangawali and Savitri ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Marmagao port is linked to the interior by means of cheap transport on rivers Zuari and Mandovi. ",
            "keyString": "105158s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jamshedpur city is located at the confluence site of rivers",
            "optionA": "  Subarnarekha and Korkai ",
            "optionB": "  Ganges and Yamuna ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi and Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Damodar and Mayurakshi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Jamshedpur city is located at the confluence site of rivers Subarnarekha and Korkai. Kharkai originates from the Chhota Nagpur Plateau and passes through the districts of West Singhbhum, Bokaro, Seraikela, East Singhbhum and Ranchi. Kharkai merges with Subarnarekha at Sankchi. In fact, Jamshedpur is situated at the confluence of the rivers Kharkai and Subarnarekha. ",
            "keyString": "105176s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following rivers flow between Vindhyan and Satpura ranges?",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Son ",
            "optionC": "  Mahe ",
            "optionD": "  Netravati ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Narmada rivers flow between Vindhyan and Satpura ranges.The Narmada originates in eastern Madhya Pradesh ( India) and flows west across the state, through a narrow valley between the Vindhya Range and spurs of the Satpura Range. It flows into the Gulf of Khambhat.",
            "keyString": "105195s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Canal irrigation is most important in the Northern Plains of India because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The soil is porous ",
            "optionB": "  The level of underground water is high ",
            "optionC": "  The sources of canals are perennial rivers ",
            "optionD": "  The region is densely populated ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Canal irrigation is most important in the Northern Plains of India because the sources of canals are perennial rivers. Perennial canals are lined to dams and barrages to provide water throughout the year, and they irrigate a vast area. ",
            "keyString": "105213s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is false?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna serves Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari serves Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi serves Bihar and Orissa ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada serves Maharashtra and Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "It originates near Trimbak in Nashik District of Maharashtra state and flows east across the Deccan Plateau into the Bay of Bengal near Narasapuram in West Godavari district of Andhra Pradesh. The river is also known as Dakshin Ganga and Gautami. ",
            "keyString": "105236s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find the odd one",
            "optionA": "  Delta ",
            "optionB": "  Bolson ",
            "optionC": "  Arc Lake ",
            "optionD": "  Creep ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Bolson is basically a desert valley usually centeredlover salt pans. Thistype of flat floored desert valley is generally surrounded by hills from all sides. ",
            "keyString": "105394s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The name of India's biggest irrigation canal is",
            "optionA": "  Yamuna Canal ",
            "optionB": "  Indira Gandhi Canal ",
            "optionC": "   Sirhind Canal ",
            "optionD": "  Upper Doab River ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Indira Gandhi Canal starts from Harike Barrage south of confluence zone of Sutlej & Beas. It is the biggest irrigation canal in India which passes through the states of Punjab, Haryana into Rajasthan, providing much needed water to deserts of Rajasthan for irrigation. Earlier it was termed \"Rajasthan Canal\".",
            "keyString": "105419s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the highest waterfall in India?",
            "optionA": "  Shimsha falls ",
            "optionB": "  Hogenakkal falls ",
            "optionC": "  Courtallam falls ",
            "optionD": "  Jog falls ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Jog falls is the highest waterfall in India located on Sharavathi River. These are also known Gerosoppa falls. ",
            "keyString": "105439s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ahmedabad is situated on the river bank of",
            "optionA": "  Sabarmati ",
            "optionB": "  Mahi ",
            "optionC": "  Luni ",
            "optionD": "  Nannada ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Ahmedabad is situated on the river bank of Sabarmati. Ahmedabad is located on the banks of the Sabarmati River, 30 km (19 mi) from the state capital Gandhinagar, which is its twin city.",
            "keyString": "105455s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The water of the Luni river is",
            "optionA": "  Fresh ",
            "optionB": "  Fresh in upper reaches and salty in the lower reaches ",
            "optionC": "  Salty ",
            "optionD": "  Fresh in rainy season and salty in other seasons ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The water of the Luni river is fresh in upper reaches and salty in the lower reaches. ",
            "keyString": "105472s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sivasamudram waterfalls is on the river",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sivasamudram waterfalls is on the river Cauvery. The Shivanasamudra Falls is on the Kaveri River after the river has found its way through the rocks and ravines of the Deccan Plateau and drops off to form waterfalls. ",
            "keyString": "105488s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Himalayan rivers are ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Monsoon fed ",
            "optionB": "  Snow fed ",
            "optionC": "  Ephemeral ",
            "optionD": "  Seasonal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Himalayan rivers are snow fed because they receive water from the melting ice of the glaciers as well as from the rains.",
            "keyString": "105505s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the highest river basin of Peninsular India",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "   Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Krishna originates from mount Mahabaleshwar from a height of about 1738m. It is a 1300km long river also known as Krishnaveni. ",
            "keyString": "105521s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a river flowing from Central India and join Yamuna/Ganga?",
            "optionA": "  Ghagra ",
            "optionB": "  Gomti ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi ",
            "optionD": "  Betwa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Betwa river also known as Vetravati river originates in Vindhyan range and flows Northward to meet Yamuna. Recently a proposal for linkage of Ken and Betwa river has come forward to transfer water from Ken Basin to Betwa Basin to feed much affected Bundelkhand region.",
            "keyString": "105670s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers of India carries the most water",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionC": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Brahmaputra rivers of India carries the most water. The mighty Brahmaputra River, which is one of the largest rivers in the world, is known by different names based on the region it flows through. The Brahmaputra Valley has an average width of about 80 Km. The main river of the valley, Brahmaputra is one of the largest rivers in the world and rank fifth with respect to its average discharge.",
            "keyString": "105697s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river originates beyond Himalaya?",
            "optionA": "  Indus ",
            "optionB": "  Saraswati ",
            "optionC": "   Ganga ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "It originates from the Northern slopes of the KailashMountain range near the Mansarovar lake in Tibetan Plateau. Primary source is called Sengge Zangbo. ",
            "keyString": "105717s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is a north flowing river?",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Chambal ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Narmada is a north flowing river. The Narmada rises at an elevation of about 3,500 feet (1,080 metres) in the Maikala Range in eastern Madhya Pradesh state on the border with Chhattisgarh state. It first follows a tortuous course through the hills near Mandla and then turns northwest to pass the city of Jabalpur.",
            "keyString": "105733s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second largest river basin in India is of the river ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The second largest river basin in India is of the river Godavari, with 3,12,812 sq km in area. ",
            "keyString": "105751s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first multi-purpose project of independent India is",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra-Nangal ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar ",
            "optionC": "  Hirakud ",
            "optionD": "  Nagarjunasagar ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Damodar Valley Corporation (DVC) was the first multipurpose project of independent India. DVC operates several hydel power stations constructed on Damodar river. ",
            "keyString": "105770s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state is not part of Narmada valley?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Narmada river after originating from Narmada Kund in Amarkantak Plateau flows through Madhya Pradesh, Gujarat and Maharastra and then drains into the Arabian Sea.",
            "keyString": "105789s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements is not correct?",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi River rises in Chattisgarh ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari River rises in Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery River rises in Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Tapti River rises in Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Kaveri also spelled Cauvery, sacred river of southern India. It rises on Brahmagiri Hill of the Western Ghats in southwestern Karnataka state, flows in a southeasterly direction for 475 miles (765 km) through the states of Karnataka and Tamil Nadu, and descends the Eastern Ghats in a series of great falls. ",
            "keyString": "105956s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Naga hills form the watershed between India and ________ ",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Myanmar ",
            "optionC": "  Bhutan ",
            "optionD": "  Bangladesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Naga hills form the watershed between India and Myanmar. ",
            "keyString": "106150s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which city is located on the banks of the river Mula-Mutha?",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Ahmedabad ",
            "optionC": "  Nagpur ",
            "optionD": "  Pune ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Mula - Mutha river is formed by confluence of Mula and Mutha rivers in Pune. After confluence of Mula and Mutha the combined river Mula-Mutha flows and joins Bhima river which in turn is a tributary to Krishna river. ",
            "keyString": "106172s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Guwahati is situated on the bank of the river",
            "optionA": "  Teesta ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionC": "  Hooghly ",
            "optionD": "  Sone ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Guwahati is an important city situated at the foothills of Shillong plateau. It is located on the bank of river Brahamputra in Assam. Guwahati has declared Gangetic river dolphin as its city animal. ",
            "keyString": "106190s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Point of origin of Indus River is",
            "optionA": "  Hindu Kush Mountain ",
            "optionB": "  Himalaya Range ",
            "optionC": "  Karakoram Range ",
            "optionD": "  Mount Kailash ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Indus river originates in Southwestern Tibet near lake Mansarovar (Mapam) in Mount Kailash range. Five Major tributaries of Indus are Beas, Chenab, Jhelum, Ravi & Sutlej. ",
            "keyString": "106208s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river originates out of India?",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionB": "  Beas ",
            "optionC": "  Ravi ",
            "optionD": "  Jhelum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The Brahamputra river originates from chenayundung glacier near lake Mansarovar in Tibet. It is know by different names in different regions. Region-Local Name Tibet - Tsangpo Chinese - Yarlung Zangbo Jiang Bangladesh- Jamuna ",
            "keyString": "106225s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers makes an estuary?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Narmada river flows through rift valley and hence is not able to pick up much sediments and flows westward into the Arabian sea. An estuary is a place where river water meets the saline water of sea. ",
            "keyString": "106384s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river Tsangpo flows through before entering India?",
            "optionA": "  Myanmar ",
            "optionB": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionC": "  Tibet ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The river Tsangpo flows through Tibet before entering India. Tsangpo or the Brahmaputra river flows 1625 km in Tibet parallel to the main range of Himalayas before entering India through Arunachal Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "106409s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Tibetan river 'Tsangpo' enters India through the State of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Nagaland ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The Tibetan river 'Tsangpo' enters India through the State of Arunachal Pradesh. The Brahmaputra enters India in the state of Arunachal Pradesh, where it is called Siang. It makes a very rapid descent from its original height in Tibet and finally appears in the plains, where it is called Dihang. ",
            "keyString": "106427s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers divides the 'Deccan Tableland' from Central Highland in northern India?",
            "optionA": "  Chambal ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Narmada rivers divides the 'Deccan Tableland' from Central Highland in northern India. Narmada river and Vindhyan range divides the Deccan Plateau into two parts. Upper part is known as central highlands and lower part is known as Deccan plateau. ",
            "keyString": "106446s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following gives the correct descending order by length of the rivers of India?",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra, Ganga, Godavari, Kosi ",
            "optionB": "  Ganga, Brahmaputra, Krishna, Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga, Godavari, Yamuna, Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Ganga, Yamuna, Godavari, Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Ganga, Godavari, Yamuna and Krishna gives the correct descending order by length of the rivers of India. ",
            "keyString": "106464s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From north towards South, which one of the following is the correct sequence of the given rivers in India?",
            "optionA": "  Shyok - Spiti - Zaskar - Sutlej ",
            "optionB": "  Shyok - Zaskar - Spiti - Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Zaskar - Shyok - Sutlej - Spiti ",
            "optionD": "  Zaskar - Sutlej - Shyok \u2013 Spiti ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Zaskar - Shyok - Sutlej - Spiti is the correct sequence of the given rivers in India from north towards South. ",
            "keyString": "106482s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ganges in Bangladesh is known as the",
            "optionA": "  Farakka ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionC": "  Padma ",
            "optionD": "  Sonar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Ganga is known as Padma in Bangladesh. After entering Bangladesh, the main branch of Ganga is known as the Padma. The Padma is joined by the Jamuna River, the largest distributary of the Brahmaputra. ",
            "keyString": "106506s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following has the, largest shipyard in India?",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Kochi ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Vishakhapatnam has the largest shipyard in India. Hindustan Shipyard Limited is a shipyard located in Visakhapatnam on the east coast of India.Founded as the Scindia Shipyard, it was built by industrialist Walchand Hirachand as a part of The Scindia Steam Navigation Company Ltd. Walchand selected Vishakhaptnam as a strategic and ideal location and took possession of land in November 1940. ",
            "keyString": "106524s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following states does not form part of the Narmada basin?",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Rajasthan does not form part of the Narmada basin. The total basin area of the river is 97,410 square kilometer comprising 85,858 square kilometer in Madhya Pradesh, 1658 square kilometer in Maharashtra and 9894 square kilometer in Gujarat. The drainage area up to dam site is 88,000 square kilometer. ",
            "keyString": "107180s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state is Jog Falls located?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Jog Falls is located in Karnataka. It is located in Sharavathi River in Shimoga district of Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "107219s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not a purpose for building Farakka Barrage?",
            "optionA": "  Checking water flowing into Bangladesh ",
            "optionB": "  Checking silting of Kolkata Port ",
            "optionC": "  Preventing erosion of Kolkata Port ",
            "optionD": "  Facilitating navigation in Ganga river ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The Farakka barrage was constructed by India in 1975 to divert water from the Ganges river system. It's main purpose was to checking water flowing in Bangladesh, checking silting of Kolkata port and erosion of Kolkata port. But recently Farakka Barrage was in news because of silting of river bed in Bihar which causes devastatingflood in Bihar.",
            "keyString": "107241s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shivasamudram falls is situated on the bank of which river",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Shivasamudram falls which are located in Karnataka are the largest waterfall in India. It is on the banks of river Cauvery. ",
            "keyString": "107264s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chandra and Bhaga the two streams join to form ________ river.",
            "optionA": "  Jhelum ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Ravi ",
            "optionD": "  Chenab ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Chandra and Bhaga the two streams join to form Chenab river. Two streams namely Chandra and Bhaga rise on the opposite sides of the Baralacha pass at an elevation of 4,891 metres and meet at Tandi at an elevation of 2,286 metres to form the river Chenab. The Chenab rises from the South-East and Bhaga from the North-West of the Baralacha pass. ",
            "keyString": "107282s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the river does not originate in Indian territory?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "It rises beyond the Indian territory in Kailash Mountain from Rakas lake near Mansarovar lake in Tibet. It is the easternmost tributary of the Indus river and is also known as Satadru. ",
            "keyString": "107301s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which from the following rivers does not originate in Indian territory?",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionC": "   Ravi ",
            "optionD": "  Chenab ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Brahamputra river originates from Chenayundung glacier near lake Mansarovar in Tibet. It is known by different names in different regions.Region - Local Name Tibet - Tsangpo Chinese Tarlung- Zangbo JiangBengal(Bangladesh) - Jamuna ",
            "keyString": "107319s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a navigable river in India?",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada ",
            "optionD": "  Chenab ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Chenab is not a navigable river in India. The waters of the Chenab were allocated to Pakistan under the terms of the Indus Waters Treaty. The river is formed by the confluence of two rivers, Chandra and Bhaga, at Tandi, 8 km southwest of Kyelang, in the Lahaul and Spiti district in the Indian state of Himachal Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "107480s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the rivers flowing westward from the Western Ghats do not form deltas because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Of the high gradient ",
            "optionB": "  They are too slow ",
            "optionC": "  They are not perennial ",
            "optionD": "  There is no vegetation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Most of the rivers flowing westward from the Western Ghats do not form deltas because of the high gradient. ",
            "keyString": "107507s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through which of the following sets of states does Krishna river flow?",
            "optionA": "  Karnataka, Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra, Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra, Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Krishna river flow through Maharashtra, Karnataka. The Krishna river's source is at Mahabaleswar near the Jor village in the extreme north of Wai Taluka, Satara District, Maharashtra in the west and empties into the Bay of Bengal at Hamasaladeevi (near Koduru) in Andhra Pradesh, on the east coast. It flows through the state of Karnataka before entering Telangana State. ",
            "keyString": "107526s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river Brahmaputra is known as ________ as it enters Arunachal Pradesh",
            "optionA": "  Dibang ",
            "optionB": "  Dihang ",
            "optionC": "  Subansiri ",
            "optionD": "  Dhansiri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Brahmaputra river originates in Tibet and flows as Tsangpo in Tibet autonomous region. Near Namcha Barua it takes a south trum and enters India making a gorge and itis called Dihang in Arunachal Pradesh. From here this river is joined by tributaries such as Dibang, Lohit and Kameng. ",
            "keyString": "107546s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Satpura range is situated between two west flowing rivers, They are",
            "optionA": "  Narmada and Luni ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada and Tapi ",
            "optionC": "  Tapi and Mahi ",
            "optionD": "  Mahi and Luni ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Satpura range is situated between two west flowing rivers, They are Narmada and Tapi. The Narmada originates in eastern Madhya Pradesh ( India) and flows west across the state, through a narrow valley between the Vindhya Range and spurs of the Satpura Range. ",
            "keyString": "107566s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one the following is a correct sequence of rivers in terms of their total basin area, in the descending order?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga, Indus, Brahmaputra, Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Indus, Ganga, Brahmaputra, Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra, Indus, Ganga, Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Indus, Ganga Godavari, Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Brahmaputra, Indus, Ganga and Godavari is a correct sequence of rivers in terms of their total basin area, in the descending order. ",
            "keyString": "107588s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The longest river of peninsular India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Cauveri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The longest river of peninsular India is Godavari. Godavari is the longest river of peninsular India. Godavari, also known as 'Dakshin Ganga' \u2013 the South Ganges, the second longest river of India after the Ganges, is the longest river of peninsular India. ",
            "keyString": "107814s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which city is located on the banks of the river Brahmaputra?",
            "optionA": "  Kanpur ",
            "optionB": "  Srinagar ",
            "optionC": "  Dibrugarh ",
            "optionD": "   Lucknow ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Dibrugarh is a city in Assam's eastern part which islocated on the bank of Brahmaputra river. It is one of the most productive tea producing cities of Assam.",
            "keyString": "107847s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers joins Ganga at Allahabad ?",
            "optionA": "  Gandak ",
            "optionB": "  Ghaghra ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Yamuna rivers joins Ganga at Allahabad. The river Yamuna joins Ganga at this point and Ganga continues to flow until it meets Bay of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "107867s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The originating point of river Godavari is",
            "optionA": "  Nasik ",
            "optionB": "  Pune ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Sholapur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Godavari river risesi Northwestern Maharashtra in Nasik. Its source of origin is Brahmagiri mountains located in Trimbakeshwar plateau. Important tributaries of river Godavari are Penganga, Wainganga Wardha, Pranahita, Manjra and Pravara. ",
            "keyString": "107884s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first river valley project started in India is",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra Nangal Project ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar Valley Project ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi Project ",
            "optionD": "  Hirakud Project ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The first river valley project started in India is Damodar Valley Project. Damodar Valley Project (DVP) is based on the model of Tennessee Valley Authority (TAV), USA constructed to harness water of Damodar, a capricious river flowing through Bihar and West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "107901s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Peninsular Indian river does not meet the Arabian Sea",
            "optionA": "  Periyar ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada ",
            "optionD": "  Tapti ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Cauvery rises in Brahmagiri hills in Karnataka and flows through Karnataka and Tamilnadu drains into the Bay of Bengal. The river basin of Cauvery comprises Kerala (3%), Karnataka (41%) and Tamilnadu (56%). Other 3 are west flowing rivers that drains into the Arabian Sea.",
            "keyString": "107920s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amravati, Bhavani, Hemavati and Kabini are tributaries of which one of the following rivers?",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Amravati, Bhavani, Hemavati and Kabini are tributaries of Cauvery. The Cauvery rises from the Brahmagiri hills in the Coorg district at 1,341 m above sea level and drain the Maysore plateau before flowing into the plain. ",
            "keyString": "107938s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Siachin Glacier's melting waters are the main source of which of the following rivers?",
            "optionA": "  Bias ",
            "optionB": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Shylok ",
            "optionD": "  Nubra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Nubra (Siachan River) is a river located to the north east of Ladakh valley. The source of this river is from Siachen glacier. ",
            "keyString": "107961s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The world's highest rail bridge being constructed in the State of Jammu & Kashmir will be on which of the following rivers?",
            "optionA": "  Jhelum ",
            "optionB": "  Chenab ",
            "optionC": "  Indus ",
            "optionD": "  Ravi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Chenab bridge built at an elevation of 359m over Chenab river is the world's highest rail bridge. It is an under construction bridge Bakkal and Kauri of Reasi district in Jammu & Kashmir. ",
            "keyString": "108143s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river Cauvery originates from which of the following states?",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The river Cauvery originates from Karnataka. Talakaveri, the place where river Kaveri originates is situated on a hill called Brahmagiri with thick forest cover in the western ghats of Karnataka in the heart of Coorg district. ",
            "keyString": "108170s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "River Indus originates from",
            "optionA": "  Hindukush range ",
            "optionB": "  Himalayan range ",
            "optionC": "  Karakoram range ",
            "optionD": "  Kailash range ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Indus is a 3,200km long trans Himalayan river. It rises from Sengge Zangbo glacier in the southwest Tibet near lake Manasarovar in the Kailash range. ",
            "keyString": "108189s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following peninsular rivers is westward flowing?",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Tapti ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Tapti peninsular rivers is westward flowing. Tapti rivers flow through the rift valleys which have a different gradient. So they flow westward. ",
            "keyString": "108207s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river Cauvery flows from ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Andhra Pradesh to Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka to Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka to Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala to Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The river Cauvery flows from Karnataka to Tamil Nadu. Originally, the Cauvery River had its source at Talakaveri in the Western Ghats Mountain Range. Talakaveri is situated in the Kodagu District in Karnataka and the river usually runs in a southeastern itinerary across the states of Karnataka and Tamil Nadu. The river flows over the southern Deccan terrains across the plains in the southeast and pours into the Bay of Bengal through two major outlets. ",
            "keyString": "108224s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The fertile land between two rivers is called",
            "optionA": "  Drainage basin ",
            "optionB": "  Watershed ",
            "optionC": "  Doab ",
            "optionD": "  Lowland or terrain ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Doab is a tract of land that lies between two conflating rivers. Punjab is a land between five rivers. ",
            "keyString": "108244s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Teesta forms a part of which major river system?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Teesta forms a part of Brahmaputra. In Bangladesh, the Brahmaputra is joined by the Teesta River, one of its largest tributaries. Below the Teesta, the Brahmaputra splits into two distributary branches. The western branch, which contains the majority of the river\u2019s flow, continues due south as the Jamuna to merge with the lower Ganges, called the Padma River. The eastern branch is called the lower or old Brahmaputra. ",
            "keyString": "108261s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true with regard to the, characteristics of the Himalayan rivers?I. Many of them have their sources in the Inner HimalayasII. They have a perennial flowIII. They have a great capacity for erosionIV. They do not form gorges",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  II and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The following that is true with regard to the, characteristics of the Himalayan rivers are Many of them have their sources in the Inner Himalayas, They have a perennial flow and They have a great capacity for erosion. ",
            "keyString": "108287s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Brahmaputra, Irrawady and Mekong rivers originate in Tibet and flow through narrow and parallel mountain ranges in their upper reaches: Of these rivers, Brahmaputra makes a \"U\" turn in its course to flow into India. This \"U\" turn is due to",
            "optionA": "  Uplift of folded Himalayan series ",
            "optionB": "  Syntaxial bending of geologically young Himalayas ",
            "optionC": "  Geo-tectonic disturbance in the tertiary folded mountain chains ",
            "optionD": "  Both (a) and (b) above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The Brahmaputra, Irrawady and Mekong rivers originate in Tibet and flow through narrow and parallel mountain ranges in their upper reaches: Of these rivers, Brahmaputra makes a \"U\" turn in its course to flow into India. This \"U\" turn is due to Uplift of folded Himalayan series and Syntaxial bending of geologically young Himalayas. ",
            "keyString": "108458s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Town located on the confluence of river Bhagirathi and Alaknanda is",
            "optionA": "  Rudraprayag ",
            "optionB": "  Devprayag ",
            "optionC": "  Vishnuprayag ",
            "optionD": "  Karnaprayag ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Two sources of river Ganga, are Bhagirathi and Alaknanda. These two rivers meet at Devprayag and then the river is called the Ganga. ",
            "keyString": "108488s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ________ river with its tributaries drains the state of Sikkim.",
            "optionA": "  Gandak ",
            "optionB": "  Kosi ",
            "optionC": "  Tista ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Tista river with its tributaries drains the state of Sikkim. The Tista River is famous for its emerald green waters. Prior to meeting the Brahmaputra River in Bangladesh as a tributary, the Tista River forms the boundary between West Bengal and Sikkim. ",
            "keyString": "108507s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers meet Ganga in Bihar ? 1. Ghaghra2. Gandak3. Son4. Punpun",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 3 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Ghaghra, Gandak, Son and Punpun rivers meet Ganga in Bihar. ",
            "keyString": "108525s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which river in the Southern Peninsula has the second largest river basin in India?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "   Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Godavari is the second longest river in India after Ganges river and it is the longest river of Peninsular India. It originates at Triambakeshwar in Maharastra andforms 2nd largest delta after Sundarban delta, which is formed by the river Ganges. Sundarban delta is also the world's largest delta. ",
            "keyString": "108542s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the features of the Himalayan rivers?I. They are of youthful nature, forming deep gorges and performing intense erosional activityII. They are free to form their courses and follow a dendritic patternIII. They have very large basins",
            "optionA": "  I and II ",
            "optionB": "  I and III ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The following are the features of the Himalayan rivers are They are of youthful nature, forming deep gorges and performing intense erosional activity, They are free to form their courses and follow a dendritic pattern and They have very large basins. ",
            "keyString": "108560s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Given here are four places situated on the banks of the Narmada :1. Jabalpur2. Mandla3. Amarkantak4. BharuchIn which order do these places occur from the source of the river to its mouth?",
            "optionA": "  3, 2, 1,4 ",
            "optionB": "  4, 3, 2, 1 ",
            "optionC": "  2, 1, 4, 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 4, 3, 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Amarkantak, Mandla, Jabalpur and Bharuch are four places situated on the banks of the Narmada from the source of the river to its mouth. ",
            "keyString": "108581s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the correct sequence of the rivers- Godavari, Mahanadi, Narmada and Tapi in the descending order of their lengths?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari - Mahanadi - Narmada - Tapi ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari - Narmada - Mahanadi - Tapi ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada - Godavart - Tapi - Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada- Tapi - Godavari \u2013 Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Godavari - Narmada - Mahanadi - Tapi is the correct sequence of the rivers in the descending order of their lengths. ",
            "keyString": "108756s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an east flowing river of the Peninsula?",
            "optionA": "  Tapi ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Mahanadi is an east flowing river of the Peninsula. Major peninsular rivers flow from west to east due to the gradient of land but narmada and tapi flows in the opposite direction because they do not flow on the plateau surface but in rift valleys and these valleys happen to have an opposite gradient. ",
            "keyString": "108788s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Punjab has a large number of inundation canals drawing water from",
            "optionA": "  Jhelum river ",
            "optionB": "  Chenab river ",
            "optionC": "   Beas river ",
            "optionD": "  Sutlej river ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sutlej river drains many canals in Punjab, Haryana and also to the Indira Gandhi canal in Rajasthan. This was recently in news because of sharing of water dispute between Punjab & Haryana. ",
            "keyString": "108808s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following States has the most critical problem of erosion of its coastal areas by the sea?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Kerala has the most critical problem of erosion of its coastal areas by the sea. This has been a critical issue in Kerala, where only 46.3 km of its 590 km long coastline has been demarcated as stable by the state fisheries department. Apart from the boulder walls, indiscriminate amount of sand quarrying from seashores have also been cited to play a massive role in erosion. ",
            "keyString": "108825s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following pairs are correctly matched?1. Narmada ________ Jabalpur2. Godavari ________ Nasik3. Mahanadi ________ CuttackSelect the correct answer using the codes given below ________ ",
            "optionA": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "All the three pairs are correctly matched: Narmada-Jabalpur, Godavari-Nasik and Mahanadi-Cuttack. ",
            "keyString": "108845s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following gives the correct sequence of ports down the western coast of India?",
            "optionA": "  Kandla, Mumbai, Kochi, Mangalore ",
            "optionB": "  Porbandar, Marmagao, Mangalore, Kochi ",
            "optionC": "  Veraval, Okha, Marmagao, Mangalore ",
            "optionD": "  Mangalore, Marmagao, Kochi, Negercoil ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Porbandar, Marmagao, Mangalore and Kochi gives the correct sequence of ports down the western coast of India. ",
            "keyString": "108862s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Bhakra Nangal Multipurpose Project is a joint venture of",
            "optionA": "  Punjab and Haryana only ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan only ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab, Haryana, Rajasthan and Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab and Himachal Pradesh only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "It is the largest and the most important multipurpose project named after the two dams built at Bhakra and Nangal on the Satluj River. It is a joint venture of the Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan states designed to harness the precious water of the Satluj for the benefit of the concerned states. ",
            "keyString": "108886s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mountain Peak located where the Tsangpo-Brahmaputra river takes a hairpin bend from West-East trend to North-South trend is",
            "optionA": "  Saramati ",
            "optionB": "  Shillong ",
            "optionC": "  Namcha Barwa ",
            "optionD": "  Karbi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Mountain Peak located where the Tsangpo-Brahmaputra river takes a hairpin bend from West-East trend to NorthSouth trend is Namcha Barwa. ",
            "keyString": "109062s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers flows between the Vindhya and Satpura ranges?",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Tapti ",
            "optionC": "  Gandak ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Narmada rivers flows between the Vindhya and Satpura ranges. The Narmada River originates from north-eastern end of Satpura & runs in the depression between the Satpura and Vindhya ranges. ",
            "keyString": "109089s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river which joins Ganga from southern side is",
            "optionA": "  Betwa ",
            "optionB": "  Chambal ",
            "optionC": "  Son ",
            "optionD": "  Ken ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Son river is an important right bank tributary of river Ganga. Betwa, Chambal and Ken are the tributaries of Yamuna which in trum is a tributary to Ganga. Son originates in in Vindhyas and flows from central India to North India.",
            "keyString": "109107s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river is known as \"Dakshin Ganga\"?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "   Mahanadi ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Dakshin Ganga is called so because as the river Ganga has the largest river basin in north India. Godavari has the largest basin in South India. ",
            "keyString": "109124s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the river known as Tsangpo in Tibet?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionC": "  Indus ",
            "optionD": "  Tista ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Brahmaputra river which originates in Tibet flows through Tibet and there it is locally known as Tsangpo(\"Purifier\"). The Chinese name of river Brahmaputra is Yarlung Zangbo. ",
            "keyString": "109140s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Chilka lake region' lies in between the deltas of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Ganga and Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari and Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi and Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna and Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The 'Chilka lake region' lies in between the deltas of Mahanadi and Godavari. Chilika Lake is a brackish water lagoon, spread over the Puri, Khurda and Ganjam districts of Odisha state on the east coast of India, at the mouth of the Daya River, flowing into the Bay of Bengal, covering an area of over 1,100 km2. ",
            "keyString": "109157s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Wular lake of Kashmir is a ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Ox- bow lake ",
            "optionB": "  Lake formed by blocking of ice ",
            "optionC": "  Lake formed by terminal morainic dam ",
            "optionD": "  Lake formed by deposition of silt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Wular lake of Kashmir is a Lake formed by terminal morainic dam. Wular Lake (also spelt Wullar) is one of the largest fresh water lakes in Asia. It is sited in Bandipora district in the Indian state of Jammu and Kashmir. The lake basin was formed as a result of tectonic activity and is fed by the Jhelum River. ",
            "keyString": "109176s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following states has the largest number of salt lakes in India?",
            "optionA": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Rajasthan has the largest number of salt lakes in India. Rajasthan is the arid state of India with average yearly rainfall appx 58-60cm. There are large number lakes mostly artificial as well as Natural Lakes.",
            "keyString": "109196s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Near the lake Mansarovar in Tibet, the river which has its source is/are ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Indus ",
            "optionB": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Near the lake Mansarovar in Tibet, the river which has its source are Indus, Sutlej and Brahmaputra. ",
            "keyString": "109351s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest Man Made Lake",
            "optionA": "  Wular ",
            "optionB": "  Gobind Sagar ",
            "optionC": "  Rana Pratap Sagar ",
            "optionD": "  Baikal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Gobind Sagar lake is the largest man made lake situated in Bilaspur district of Himachal Pradesh. After Gobind Sagar Dhebar lake in Rajasthan is largest artificial lake. ",
            "keyString": "109375s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following pairs: Tributary River Main River1. Chambal Narmada2. Sone Yamuna3. Manas BrahmaputraWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  3 only ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Manas Brahmaputra is correctly matched. The Manas river is a major tributary of Brahmaputra River, which passes through the heart of the national park. ",
            "keyString": "109392s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an east following river of Indian Peninsula?",
            "optionA": "  Tapti ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Periyar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Mahanadi is an east following river of Indian Peninsula. Most of the major rivers of the peninsula such as the Mahanadi, the Godavari, the Krishna and the Kaveri flow eastwards and drain into the Bay of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "109411s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the longest river of Peninsular India?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The longest river of Peninsular India is Godavari with a length of 1465km. It is also known as Vridha Ganga or Dakshin Ganga. ",
            "keyString": "109427s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following group of rivers in India are likely to show the least erosional activity?",
            "optionA": "  Himalayan rivers ",
            "optionB": "  Those rising in the Great Plain of India ",
            "optionC": "  The thin streams flowing into the Arabian Sea ",
            "optionD": "  The eastward flowing Peninsular rivers ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "The eastward flowing Peninsular rivers are likely to show the least erosional activity. These rivers are involved less in the erosional and depositional activities. ",
            "keyString": "109444s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following east flowing rivers of India forms rift valley due to down warping?",
            "optionA": "  Damodar ",
            "optionB": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionC": "  Son ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Damodar east flowing rivers of India forms rift valley due to down warping. Down warp denotes a segment of the earth\u2019s crust that is broadly bent downward.",
            "keyString": "109465s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hinterland refers to ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Continental shelf in the sea from which oil can be extracted ",
            "optionB": "  Natural harbour used for international trade ",
            "optionC": "  Land region extending from a sea port ",
            "optionD": "  Abandoned sea port where trade was carried out initially ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Hinterland refers to land region extending from a sea port. The hinterland is a land space over which a transport terminal, such as a port, sells its services and interacts with its users.",
            "keyString": "109636s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Plateau that has both West and East flowing drainage system is",
            "optionA": "  Malwa ",
            "optionB": "  Chota Nagpur ",
            "optionC": "  Ranchi ",
            "optionD": "  Hazaribagh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Malwa region is in west-central part of India occupying a plateau of volcanic origin. The Mahi and the Chambal river drain the central part of this plateau, while the Betwa river and the headwaters of the Dhasan and Ken rivers drain the east of the plateau. ",
            "keyString": "109662s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which name does the Brahmaputra enter into India?",
            "optionA": "  Manas ",
            "optionB": "  Dhansiri ",
            "optionC": "  Dihang ",
            "optionD": "  Tsangpo ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Brahmaputra enters India in the state of Arunachal Pradesh, where it is called Dihang. It makes a very rapid descent from its original height in Tibet and finally appears in the plains, where it is called Dihang. ",
            "keyString": "109681s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Canal irrigation is most important in north India because the",
            "optionA": "  Soil is porous ",
            "optionB": "  Level of underground water is high ",
            "optionC": "  Sources of the canals are the perennial rivers ",
            "optionD": "  Regions is densely populated ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Canal irrigation is most important in north India because the sources of the canals are the perennial rivers. ",
            "keyString": "109699s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?",
            "optionA": "  India ranks 9th in the world's shipping tonnage ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai port handles half of the country's foreign trade ",
            "optionC": "  Kandla and Kolkata are tidal ports ",
            "optionD": "  India has 14 major ports and 129 minor ports ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Mumbai port handles half of the country's foreign trade. Mumbai has a natural harbor and it is the biggest seaport of the country. Mumbai port is situated closer to the general routes from the countries of Middle East, Mediterranean countries, North Africa, Europe, and North America where the major share of country\u2019s overseas trade is carried out. ",
            "keyString": "109719s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river is known as India's River of Sorrow?",
            "optionA": "  Hooghly ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar ",
            "optionC": "  Ghaghara ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Kosi river in India situated in Bihar and Jharkhand is known as \u201cSorrow of Bihar\u201d or \u201cRiver of Sorrow\" in India. Some times Brahmaputra is also called \u201cRiver of Sorrow\" as Kosi river changes its course while Brahmaputra overflows and causes floods during rainy season. ",
            "keyString": "109883s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following pairs:Tributary -  Main Rivera. Chambal - Narmadab. Son  -  Yamunac. Manas  - BrahmaputraWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched",
            "optionA": "  a, b and c ",
            "optionB": "  a and b only ",
            "optionC": "  a and c only ",
            "optionD": "  c only ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Tributary-Main river Chambal-Yamuna Son-Ganga Manas-Brahamputra ",
            "keyString": "109914s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Peninsular rivers which do not join the Arabian Sea are",
            "optionA": "  Narmada and Tapi ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada and Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari and Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Tapi and Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The Peninsular rivers which do not join the Arabian Sea are Godavari and Krishna. ",
            "keyString": "109932s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers is known as 'Vridha Ganga'?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Godavari rivers is known as 'Vridha Ganga' because of its large size and extent among the peninsular rivers. ",
            "keyString": "109949s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cities is not located on a river bank?",
            "optionA": "  Surat ",
            "optionB": "  Agra ",
            "optionC": "  Cuttack ",
            "optionD": "  Mysore ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Mysore city is not located on a river bank. The city is located between two rivers: the Kaveri River that flows through the north of the city and the Kabini River, a tributary of the Kaveri, that lies to the south. ",
            "keyString": "109966s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lake Sambhar is nearest to which one of the following cities of Rajasthan?",
            "optionA": "  Bharatpur ",
            "optionB": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionC": "  Jodhpur ",
            "optionD": "  Udaipur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Lake Sambhar is nearest to Jaipur. Sambhar, situated in the Indian state of Rajasthan, is a municipality of Jaipur and is also popularly known as the Salt Lake City.",
            "keyString": "109984s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sardar Sarovar dam is being built on the river",
            "optionA": "  Tapti ",
            "optionB": "  Mahi ",
            "optionC": "  Chambal ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sardar Sarovar is a gravity dam on river Narmada. It is located in Alirajpur district of Madhya Pradesh. Despite popular protest Supreme Court has given directions to increase its height. ",
            "keyString": "110001s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Pong Dam' is constructed on the river",
            "optionA": "  Ravi ",
            "optionB": "  Tapti ",
            "optionC": "  Beas ",
            "optionD": "  Don ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Pong dam also known as Maharana Pratap Sagar is the highest earthfill dam constructed across the river Beas. It is located in Kangra district of Himachal Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "110017s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Nagarjuna Sagar dam is constructed on the river",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "   Chambal ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi ",
            "optionD": "  Sutlej ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Nagarjuna Sagar dam is built across the Krishna river. It is located on the border of Telangana and Andhra Pradesh was opened in 1967.",
            "keyString": "110035s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which dam of India is the highest?",
            "optionA": "  Mettur ",
            "optionB": "  Rihand ",
            "optionC": "  Thein ",
            "optionD": "  Bhakra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Bhakra Nangal dam across Sutlej river in Himachal Pradesh is the highest among the given options. Its height is 225 meters. Its reservoir is known as Gobinda Sagar Lake. ",
            "keyString": "110054s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following port caters to the export of Kudremukh iron ore?",
            "optionA": "  Cochin ",
            "optionB": "  New Mangalore ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "New Mangalore port, located in Karnataka caters to the export of iron ore concentrates from Kudremukh mines. ",
            "keyString": "110225s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"The Dowlaiswaram Anicut\" is an important canal system in the",
            "optionA": "  Godavari Delta ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna Delta ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga Delta ",
            "optionD": "  Cauvery Delta ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\"The Dowlaiswaram Anicut\" is an important canal system in the Godavari Delta. In 1863, Sir Arthur Cotton, who built the Dowlaiswaram Anicut on the Godavari, proclaimed that the British Empire \u201chad command of all the water of India\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "110249s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following seaports ________ 1. Chennai2. Machilipattinam3. Nagapattinam4. Tuticorin The correct sequence of these ports as one moves from north to south is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  1, 2, 3, 4 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 1, 3, 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 3, 2, 4 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 1, 4, 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Machilipattinam, Chennai, Nagapattinam and Tuticorin is the correct sequence of these ports as one moves from north to south. ",
            "keyString": "110271s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following canals is located in West Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  Lower Ganga Canal ",
            "optionB": "  Sarada Canal ",
            "optionC": "  Eden Canal ",
            "optionD": "  Sirhind Canal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Eden canal derives its water from Durgapur Barrage built across Damodar river in West Bengal. It is a part of Damodar river valley project. ",
            "keyString": "110290s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rajasthan Canal Project cover",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Haryana ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Rajasthan Canal Project cover Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan. Forty-nine percent of the project's canal command area (CCA) is in Haryana, 35 percent in Punjab, and 16 percent Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "110307s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second largest basin in Peninsular India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery Basin ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari Basin ",
            "optionC": "  Narmada Basin ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna Basin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Godavari a 1465 km long river that originates from Trimbakeshwar in the Nashik district of Maharashtra. It receives all its water through a basin of area about 312812 sq. km. ",
            "keyString": "110325s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The port especially developed for exporting iron ore to Japan is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Haldia ",
            "optionB": "  New Tuticorin ",
            "optionC": "  Paradeep ",
            "optionD": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The port especially developed for exporting iron ore to Japan is Paradeep. Paradip Port is a natural, deep-water port on the East coast of India in Jagatsinghpur district of Odisha. It is situated at confluence of the Mahanadi river and the Bay of Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "110343s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the followings pairs is wrongly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Koyana Project  -  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Sharavathy Project - Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "   Balimela Project - Odisha ",
            "optionD": "  Sabarigiri Project - Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Project - StateKoyana -Maharashtra Sharavathy - KarnatakaBalimela - OdishaSabarigiri - Kerala ",
            "keyString": "110361s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many ports are there in India?",
            "optionA": "  6 ",
            "optionB": "  9 ",
            "optionC": "  10 ",
            "optionD": "  12 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Although there are 13 major sea ports in India 12 of them are major ports of Government whereas Ennore port of Chennai is a corporate one. ",
            "keyString": "110379s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Sivasamudram Falls is on ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionB": "  Subernarekha ",
            "optionC": "  Indravati ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The Sivasamudram Falls is on Cauvery. Shivanasamudra is a small island town in the Mandya district of Karnataka. It is 65 km east of Mysore and 120 km from Bangalore. Situated on the banks of the river Cauvery, the area is surrounded by forested hills and lush green valleys. ",
            "keyString": "110395s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On the tributary of which river has Riband Dam been constructed?",
            "optionA": "  Chambal ",
            "optionB": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionC": "  Son ",
            "optionD": "  Periyar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Rihand dam/Govind Ballabh Pant Sagar is located on Rihand river which is a tributary of Son river which intum is a right bank tributary to river Ganga. It is located in Uttar Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "110552s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which of the following sets of rivers are Nagarjunasagar, Ukai, Hirakud, and Thein Dam located respectively?",
            "optionA": "  Krishna, Mahanadi, Godavari, Tapi ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery, Krishna, Narmada, Beas ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna, Tapi, Mahanadi, Ravi ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari, Brahmaputra, Narmada, Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "On Krishna, Tapi, Mahanadi and Ravi sets of rivers are Nagarjunasagar, Ukai, Hirakud, and Thein Dam located respectively. ",
            "keyString": "110588s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The longest dam in India is",
            "optionA": "  Bhakra Dam ",
            "optionB": "  Nagarjuna Sagar Dam ",
            "optionC": "  Hirakund Dam ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi Dam ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Hirakund dam which is situated over Mahanadi river is 25 km long dam. It is situated in tribal state Odisha. Hirakund reservoir is 55 km long. ",
            "keyString": "110608s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "River Damodar is called 'Sorrow of Bengal' because it ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Gets flooded often causing havoc ",
            "optionB": "  Causes maximum soil erosion ",
            "optionC": "  Forms number of dangerous waterfalls ",
            "optionD": "  Is not a perennial river ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "River Damodar is called 'Sorrow of Bengal' because it gets flooded often causing havoc. ",
            "keyString": "110624s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hidkal Dam is on the river",
            "optionA": "  Krishna ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "  Pennar ",
            "optionD": "  Ghataprabha ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Hidkal Dam is on the river Ghataprabha. Hidkal Dam is situated at Hukkeri in Belgaum district of Karnataka. It is constructed across the Ghataprabha River. The dam is an archaeologically relevant site. ",
            "keyString": "110641s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The second largest river system in India, next to the Ganga system, is that of ________.",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmani ",
            "optionD": "  Baitarni ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The second largest river system in India, next to the Ganga system, is that of Godavari. The Godavari is the second longest river in India after the river Ganga and also forms one of the largest river basins in India. The River is sacred to Hindus and Godavari delta are the second largest mangrove formation in the country. ",
            "keyString": "110659s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of Peninsular rivers?",
            "optionA": "  Seasonal flow ",
            "optionB": "  Meandering tendency often shifting their beds ",
            "optionC": "  Flow through shallow valleys ",
            "optionD": "  Little erosional activity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Meandering tendency often shifting their beds is not a characteristic of Peninsular rivers. They flow through open and graded shallow valleys with low gradients and little erosion. They have meandering tendencies, often shifting their beds. Most of these rivers can be said to have reached a mature state of development. ",
            "keyString": "110677s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers of the Indian sub-continent covers the longest distance from its source to the sea into",
            "optionA": "  Indus ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The rivers of the Indian sub-continent covers the longest distance from its source to the sea into is Ganga. ",
            "keyString": "110701s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indira Gandhi canal gets water from which river",
            "optionA": "  Sutlej and Beas ",
            "optionB": "  Ravi and Beas ",
            "optionC": "  Ravi and Chenab ",
            "optionD": "  Beas only ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Indira Gandhi canal starts from Harike barrage which is located a few kilometers below the meeting point of Sutlej & Beas rivers and it derives its water from there. ",
            "keyString": "110853s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bhakra Nangal Project is constructed across which river?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionC": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Under the river valley development project a concrete gravity dam named Bhakra Nangal dam has been built over Sutlej river in Bilaspur district of Himachal Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "110878s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following lakes in India has the highest Water salinity?",
            "optionA": "  Dal ",
            "optionB": "  Chilka ",
            "optionC": "  Wular ",
            "optionD": "  Sambhar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sambhar lake in India has the highest water salinity. Sambhar Salt Lake of Rajasthan is largest inland salt lake of India and an extensive saline wetland. ",
            "keyString": "110895s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is Lonar Lake situated?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Lonar is a crater lake located in Buldhana district of Maharashtra. This saline soda lake has been notified as a National Geo-Heritage Monument. ",
            "keyString": "110912s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Loktak Lake, a big lake of North East India, is located in",
            "optionA": "  Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Tripura ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Loktak Lake, a big lake of North East India, is located in Manipur. Loktak Lake is an intriguing ecosystem in the Northeast state of Manipur, which still remains largely untapped. This wonder lake situated at a distance of 53 km from Imphal is, however, one of those places in Manipur where foreigners are allowed a visit. ",
            "keyString": "110928s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Naini lake is in",
            "optionA": "  Nainital ",
            "optionB": "  Mussorie ",
            "optionC": "  Rishikesh ",
            "optionD": "  Pushkar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "The famous Naini lake is in Nainital. Nainital Lake, famously known as Naini Lake is the major attraction of Naintal town as well of Uttarakhand. Surrounded by panoramic seven hills, Nainital lake is a favourite spot among romantic travellers around the world. ",
            "keyString": "110950s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Govind Ballabh Pant Sagar which has the distinction of being the largest man-made lake in Asia, forms part of",
            "optionA": "  Damodar Valley Project ",
            "optionB": "  Chambal Project ",
            "optionC": "  Tehri Dam ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi Project ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Govind ballabh pant sagar which has the distinction of being the largest man-made lake in asia, forms part of Chambal Project. Chambal project is a joint venture of Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh state governments. It aims at judicious utilization of the water resources of the river for irrigation, power generation, soil conservation and economic development of the region. ",
            "keyString": "110971s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the longest river in India",
            "optionA": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionB": "  Ganga ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Krishna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Although river Brahmaputra is one of the longest rivers having a length of about 2900 km but in India it flows for only 916 km. River Ganga which flows for 2,525km is the longest river in India. ",
            "keyString": "111148s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which river is called 'The Sorrow of Bengal'?",
            "optionA": "  Sone ",
            "optionB": "  Damodar ",
            "optionC": "  Hooghly ",
            "optionD": "  Kosi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Damodar River\u00a0was earlier\u00a0known as the \"River\u00a0of Sorrows\" because it used to flood many areas of Bardhaman, Hooghly, Howrah and Medinipur districts. Even now the floods sometimes affect the lower\u00a0Damodar Valley, but the havoc it wreaked in earlier years is now a matter of history. The floods were virtually an annual ritual. ",
            "keyString": "111173s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river basin which is called 'Ruhr of India' is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Damodar ",
            "optionB": "  Hooghly ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Swarnarekha ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Damodar valley is called Ruhr of India because it is rich in minerals ,specifically coal, which led to the development of many industries in the valley region especially iron and steel industries. ",
            "keyString": "111192s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river on which the reservoir for Indira Gandhi Canal has been built is",
            "optionA": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionB": "  Ravi ",
            "optionC": "  Luni ",
            "optionD": "  Jhelum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Indira Gandhi Canal starts from Harike Barrage. This Barrage acts as a reservoir to the water from confluence of rivers Sutlej and Beas. From here it derives water and fed the Rajasthan state. ",
            "keyString": "111209s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "River Godavari flows through ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra, Orissa and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra, Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra, Karnataka, Orissa and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "River Godavari flows through Maharashtra and Andhra Pradesh. The source of the Godavari River is situated near Trimbak in Nashik District of Maharashtra. After setting off, the river runs towards the east, traversing the Deccan Plateau. In the end, the river empties into the Bay of Bengal at Narasapuram in West Godavari district, Andhra Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "111274s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Indira Gandhi Canal\", which is around 450 km long, provides irrigation facility mainly to which of the following states?",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Haryana ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\"Indira Gandhi Canal\", which is around 450 km long, provides irrigation facility mainly to Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "111297s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following tributaries of the Ganga System flows northwards?",
            "optionA": "  Kosi ",
            "optionB": "  Ghaghara ",
            "optionC": "  Gandak ",
            "optionD": "  Son ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Son tributaries of the Ganga System flows northwards. There are many tributaries of river Ganga. Major left-bank tributaries include Gomti (Gumti), Ghaghara (Gogra), Gandaki (Gandak), and Kosi (Kusi); major right-bank tributaries include Yamuna (Jumna), Son, Punpun and Damodar. ",
            "keyString": "111314s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Proposed Sea way \"Sethusamudram\" is the canal passes through which sea-lanes?",
            "optionA": "  Gulf of Mannar ",
            "optionB": "  Malacca Strait ",
            "optionC": "  Gulf of Kutch ",
            "optionD": "  Andaman and Nicobar islands ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "It is a shipping canal project to create a shipping route in the Palk Strait to provide continuous route around Indian Peninsula. ",
            "keyString": "111333s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Loktak\" is a",
            "optionA": "  Valley ",
            "optionB": "  Lake ",
            "optionC": "  River ",
            "optionD": "  Mountain range ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Loktak is a lake which is situated in Manipur. It is largest freshwater lake in Northeast India. It is famous for Phumdis (floating mass). Only floating national park i.e. Keibul Lamjao National Park is located in it. ",
            "keyString": "111353s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a tributary of the Ganga?",
            "optionA": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionB": "  Son ",
            "optionC": "  Gomti ",
            "optionD": "  Sutlej ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sutlej is not a tributary of the Ganga. It is the easternmost tributary of the Indus River. The waters of the Sutlej are allocated to India under the Indus Waters Treaty between India and Pakistan, and are mostly diverted to irrigation canals in India. ",
            "keyString": "111370s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following cities is not located on the bank of river Ganga?",
            "optionA": "  Fatehpur ",
            "optionB": "  Bhagalpur ",
            "optionC": "  Uttarkashi ",
            "optionD": "  Kanpur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Uttarkashi city is not located on the bank of river Ganga. Uttarkashi is situated on the banks of river Bhagirathi at an altitude of 1158 m above sea level. Uttarkashi is generally known as a holy town close to Rishikesh.",
            "keyString": "111388s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nasik is located on the bank of which river?",
            "optionA": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionB": "  Tapti ",
            "optionC": "  Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Godavari originates from Brahmagiri Mountain, Trimbakeshwar in Nashik and flows through the city. Other towns located on the banks of river Godavari are Adilabad, Nanded, Basara and Trimbakeshwar. ",
            "keyString": "111412s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vijayawada is located on the bank of which river?",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Krishna river originates near Mahabaleshwar in Sahyadri and flows through Maharashtra, Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh. Vijaywada is a town in Andhra Pradesh located on the bank of this river.",
            "keyString": "111483s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Surat is located on the bank of which river?",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Sharawati ",
            "optionC": "  Mahi ",
            "optionD": "  Tapti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Tapti or Tapi river flows from east to west through the states of M.P., Maharashtra and Gujarat. Surat is a city in Gujarat located on the bank of this river. ",
            "keyString": "111505s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The total length of the river Ganga is about",
            "optionA": "  3000 km ",
            "optionB": "  3425 km ",
            "optionC": "  2500 km ",
            "optionD": "  2750 km ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "The total length of the river Ganga is about 2500 km. The length of the Ganges is frequently said to be slightly over 2,500 km (1,600 mi) long, about 2,505 km (1,557 mi), to 2,525 km (1,569 mi), or perhaps 2,550 km (1,580 mi). ",
            "keyString": "111522s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "River Cauvery flows through the state of",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra and Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka, Kerala and Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh, Gujarat and Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala, Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "River Cauvery flows through the state of Karnataka, Kerala and Tamil Nadu. ",
            "keyString": "111539s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Narmada river originates from Amarkantak in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Narmada river originates from Amarkantak in Madhya Pradesh. River Narmada emerges from Amarkantak Hill of Maikal Range. Son river is largest of southern tributaries of Ganga that originates near Amarkantak in Madhya Pradesh near the source of Narmada River. Damodar originates in Chandwa on the Chota Nagpur Plateau. The Tapi River originates in the Betul district. ",
            "keyString": "111558s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following river flows from the sediments in India?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Ganga river flows through the Northern plains carrying huge amount of sediments. Moreover a great amount of sediments are also added by its tributaries such as Kosi, Gandak, Son, Ghaggar and Yamuna.",
            "keyString": "111616s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Narmada river originate in",
            "optionA": "  Vindhyan Range ",
            "optionB": "  Maikal Range ",
            "optionC": "  Satpura Range ",
            "optionD": "  Mahadeo Range ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Narmada river originate in Maikal Range. Amarkantak is the place from where the Narmada river originates. It rises from the Maikal ranges at the height of 1057 meter above the sea level. ",
            "keyString": "111638s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers flows through Maharashtra and Gujarat ?",
            "optionA": "  Sabarmati ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Mahi ",
            "optionD": "  Tapti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Tapti rivers flows through Maharashtra and Gujarat. The Tapi is the second largest westward draining inter-state river basin. It covers a large area in the State of Maharashtra besides areas in the states of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "111656s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ofthe following river is beyond the Himalaya?",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Ravi ",
            "optionC": "   Sutlej ",
            "optionD": "  Yamuna ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "Sutlej river originates beyond the Himalayas in the Kailash range. It provides water to many canals in Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan including India Gandhi canel. ",
            "keyString": "111673s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The river system which depends more on melting of snow for its water supply is the",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmaputra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The river system which depends more on melting of snow for its water supply is the Indus. The Indus basin heavily depends on its upstream mountainous part for the downstream supply of water while downstream demands are high.",
            "keyString": "111691s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where do river Bhagirathi and Alaknanda meet?",
            "optionA": "  Karnprayag ",
            "optionB": "  Devprayag ",
            "optionC": "  Rudraprayag ",
            "optionD": "  Gangotri ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "The Alaknanda river rises at feet of Satopanth and Bhagirath kharak Glacier and then it meets the headwaters of Bhagirathi at Devprayag (830 m) from where onwards it flow as Ganga. ",
            "keyString": "111708s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "River Luni drains into",
            "optionA": "  Kerala Coast ",
            "optionB": "  Ganga delta ",
            "optionC": "  Godavari delta ",
            "optionD": "  Rann of Kachchh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "River Luni drains into Rann of Kachchh. Luni River, also called Luni, river in Rajasthan state, western India. Rising on the western slopes of the Aravalli Range near Ajmer, where it is known as the Sagarmati, the river flows generally southwestward through the hills and across the plains of the region. It then enters a patch of desert before it finally dissipates into the wastes of the northeastern part of the marsh called the Rann of Kachchh (Kutch) in Gujarat state.",
            "keyString": "111725s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An important river of Indian desert is",
            "optionA": "  Luni ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "   Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Beas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Luni river which originates in Pushkar Valley of Aravali range flows through the Thar Desert. It is an inland river i.e. it does not meet with the sea and disappear in land. ",
            "keyString": "111787s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following rivers, which one is the longest?",
            "optionA": "  Godavari ",
            "optionB": "  Krishna ",
            "optionC": "  Mahanadi ",
            "optionD": "  Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Godavari is the longest among the following. Godavari is the longest river in Andhra Pradesh, With a length of 1465 km, it is the second longest river in India, after the Ganges. ",
            "keyString": "111807s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following pairs-Tributary   -  Main river1. Chambal  -  Yamuna2. Son   -  Narmada3. Manas   -  BrahmaputraWhich of the following is correctly matched",
            "optionA": "  1, 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionC": "   1,2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  Only 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Son river is a right bank tributary of river Ganga, whereas Chambal and Manas are respective tributaries of rivers Yamuna and Brahmaputra.",
            "keyString": "111824s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the fullowing river forms estuary?",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionC": "   Krishna ",
            "optionD": "  Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "Narmada river flows through a rift valley between Vindhyas in North and Satpura in South so it carries minimal amount of sediments and forms Estuary instead Delta.",
            "keyString": "111841s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following rivers flows through a rift valley?",
            "optionA": "  Cauvery ",
            "optionB": "  Narmada ",
            "optionC": "  Kosi ",
            "optionD": "  Godavari ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "Narmada rivers flows through a rift valley. It is one of the rivers in India that flows in a rift valley, flowing west between the Satpura and Vindhya ranges.",
            "keyString": "111858s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following States is Sambhar lake located?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "Sambhar lake is located in Rajasthan. Sambhar Lake in Rajasthan is India's biggest salt Lake. Sambhar lake is located near the Jaipur city at a distance of 85 km.",
            "keyString": "111876s37m41h19d24m6y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}

